One thing that's more important than models is the agent that you choose.
When we notice value that bumps up, it's not always the model that's improving
so much.
It's typically the agent. But one thing above
that — when we actually identify, "oh, we're one-shotting this a ton more" —
this is, you know, it's understanding what we want to do.
It's really the quality of the context that really makes
the model sing and really, really work well.
Oh, no. Oh!
So thank you very much for coming to this session.
We had over 100 people register, and
a fine few fellows and ladies joined us.
I must admit, I'm probably questioning your thought process,
because it's lovely outside,
and I'd probably prefer to be outside in the garden, maybe
with a beer or something like that. So thank you,
nevertheless, for coming to join us.
I thought I was giving a
different session, but this is "Context is King" — over the last 30 minutes
so I've just been trying
to cram a 75-minute session into what's hopefully going to be 20 minutes.
So here we go.
Apologies if we go a little bit over, but this is a session:
Context is King.
And I really want to kind of focus on the value
that context gives us when we're building with agents.
Now, 2025 — last year — it was all about how we as companies
can go as fast as we possibly can, or rather, as fast as we can adopt agents.
So how can we increase our usage of agents as much as possible?
This year it's all about: how can we use them effectively?
How can we get the most out of them?
How can we get value out of them?
And that ROI in terms of what we're spending?
And this really comes down
to a number of things, but one of them is the model you choose.
So obviously tokens cost money.
Some are going to be better than others.
But one thing that's better — as we've found out — than models,
or more important than models, is the agent that you choose.
Because when we notice value that bumps up, it's not always the model
that's improving so much.
It's typically the agent that rotates
and loops, getting the best out of the model.
But one thing above that:
when we actually identify, "oh, we're one-shotting this a ton more" —
this is, you know, it's understanding what we want to do.
It's really the quality of the context that really makes
the model sing and really, really work well.
So context, for me, is how you get the most
out of your agent, and getting the most out of your agent —
or rather, using an agent — is how you get the most out of your model.
So these three things
in combination will get you to that real value.
Let me give you a quick example.
This is something I did a little while back, actually.
So numbers may change,
but here you can see I'm actually running some tests against a skill.
And in this case the skill is the "first to five best practices" skill.
And you can see I'm using several models with several agents here:
Opus, Sonnet, and Haiku.
And you can see the scores that they get in terms of how good
every single model is performing on certain tasks.
And you can see — yes, you would expect Opus to do well —
but with the skill there's actually not as much of a difference between them.
And when you think about the cost that is incurred with these,
the actual value, the ROI, is actually far, far smaller —
the difference between these models —
once you've started using context and using skills.
Okay.
So we've talked about context a little bit,
but what do we mean by context?
This is an important question.
Well, anything that the agent can really access — whether that's in its memory,
whether it's the files that are local to the system,
whether it's things that we load in like skills and rules,
whether it's documentation around, you know, third-party libraries
or our own proprietary libraries that we create and provide to it.
It could be even our messages —
all that adds up as context for the agent — and test outputs,
whether it's linters or whatever that gets run and passed back in.
All of this becomes context.
And then we'll dig into a couple.
The first one we're going to look at is rules,
and how you can use rules within your agent as context.
Now, rules are essentially constraints — behavioural constraints —
that an agent will always read.
Typically these tend to be in something like —
not sure if I've got this — something like a CLAUDE.md:
things that the agent will always go through.
These are things that you should always do, not just based on
what the user is asking — but you should always do these things.
Very often: organisational rules and things like that.
Skills, on the other hand,
are much more dependent on the actual task or the act that the agent's doing.
So they're kind of like — you can think of them a little bit
more like callable procedures. When you need them,
you call them, you invoke them.
They're not always fully read.
They're disclosed progressively,
as and when the agent feels like it wants to use that thing.
There are a couple of reasons why
sometimes it will or won't use it.
If it thinks it can do something itself, it may not actually use
the skill. But we'll look at that in a little bit.
So the practical distinction is: rules are passively run.
They're always there, and they shape everything the agent does.
A skill is triggered for that specific job.
When we look at a SKILL.md, we'll dig a little bit deeper into skills.
Now there are really two pieces of this: metadata at the very top,
which are mandatory —
the name and the description.
And the description, of course, is super important, because that's —
well, the name and the description are all that
the agent has to load in order to know whether it activates it or not.
And an activation of a skill is an agent saying, "Look,
I think I need more information in this skill to perform this task.
I will read more, and I will load more of that skill into context."
And it can choose how much of that skill it does load into context based
on the task.
So when we
think about skill activation, it goes from knowing
nothing to knowing exactly what it needs — like in an instant.
And that's the key.
So the way it does this is by loading things into the context window.
Now the context window is essentially a finite piece of memory —
a finite area that contains a number of everything that I said:
files in the file system, skills, maybe project files or user files.
And there's absolutely a Goldilocks zone.
Don't be thinking that area —
that context window — I can fill it completely
and an agent will work
just as well with a full context window as with a small context window.
The Goldilocks zone is: if you provide too little context for a task,
it will perform the task, but it may not do it the way you wish
that task to be carried out.
So maybe it makes decisions that you'd actually prefer
things being done in a different way.
When there's too much context, it overwhelms the agent.
And when you overwhelm the agent, you effectively degrade
the performance, because it's actually missing key pieces of information.
So what you want is the Goldilocks zone — this "just right" zone.
If you haven't heard of the Goldilocks zone
— obviously there's the Three Bears — but I'd love to
think of it as the distance from a star
at which a planet has to be to actually hold life.
Too close: it's too hot.
Too far: the bacteria, etc., etc.,
won't grow. So that's the Goldilocks zone.
So you can always see your context state — context include code, for example — and you'll see
how your context window is filled.
And like I say,
there are a bunch of different window sizes.
But don't be fooled into thinking you can completely
fill that window without the performance degrading.
Okay.
You can also — just as well as adding things to the window —
you can obviously free up those tokens, and you can do that through compaction.
It happens automatically — using things like, well,
when you fill up your context window you'll get automatic compaction.
One thing that people don't always know is you can compact very often
with instructions afterwards — to say, when you do it manually, compact.
"I want to do this thing afterwards," and it will summarise
based on knowledge of what you are trying to achieve next.
So it'll keep things in the context window so that it doesn't
have to reload anything else in, because it knows
enough of what to do next.
Cool.
I'm going to do a skills demo, and then we're going to jump through
potential problems that we as an organisation
may face when doing this more at scale.
So as part of this skills demo, what I'm going to do is actually
show you an app that I've been working on over the last couple of days,
which is called "Talk to Skill."
Oh cool, it's just finished. That's awesome.
Talk to Skill is an application that uses a skill itself.
But we're going to be running this live at Dev Con —
the conference that was just mentioned.
And what we're going to do
is turn every single talk, every single session, into a skill.
Why would you want to do that?
Well, maybe you want to ask some Q&A of
that speaker — currently, that speaker — maybe you want to learn
or bounce some ideas off someone, or say, "How do I do this with my project?"
And you can use that skill to get good advice from the lessons
learned in the session with your scenario.
So in this case, just today, Guy — our founder —
practically demoed his session, the keynote session,
at our weekly lunch and learn at lunchtime.
Now, what this does is it actually takes from a Granola folder.
So every single time a Granola transcript is captured, it throws it into a folder.
And when we recognise that — this refreshes every 30 seconds or so for now —
when we recognise something new comes in, we have a skill
that automatically creates a session skill and publishes it across to —
then it does a number of other steps, which I'll go into in just a second.
But here I can see — if I come here —
here I can see we have the full transcript.
We have a bunch of quotes.
We have a tile JSON.
So this is the version of the skill which we've uploaded into Tessl,
and an outline that describes, you know,
essentially what the session is about.
And this SKILL.md, which has a name, it has a description,
and some other things — how to use this skill, and so forth.
Now, if I come over here, you will see I have this
skill that exists. I can install it —
so I can run npm install — and I'll do that in just a second.
And information
about how to use this skill and the kinds of things that I should do.
So let's go ahead and actually play with this.
So if I was to run a test install — or in fact, let's just
copy and paste and use that straight out of the box — I've now installed
that tile or that plugin, which contains the skill, into my environment.
Now, if I run Claude and say,
"Tell me about thinking start" —
tell me why
I should
consider
context to be like code —
let's see if it auto-activates my skill.
There we go. It's activated that skill.
It reads the outline.
It's obviously doing some work
and actually loading the relevant pieces into my context.
And it should hopefully — depending on
how Claude is today, who's still using Claude?
I've heard so many people switching — who switched
from Claude to Cursor in the last two weeks.
Last month, a few people — three people.
Very, very interesting.
I was just talking with Alan in the office just now.
I was saying,
"My God, I just asked it to create me a very simple skill for this demo.
And it's taken three minutes to create a pirate skill. Like,
why is it taking so long?"
And I think it's just the deep thinking that's just taking — it's just crazy.
Anyway, where was I?
Okay.
Skills are already behaving like code.
It gives me quotes, it gives me more information.
And now I might actually say, "Okay, what do I do to this skill?
What do I do to this skill
to treat it like code?" It will probably say, "Okay, you need to version it.
You need to do these various things."
I might say, "Tell me" —
he talks about the — he talks about a CDLC.
I can see it there.
There's the clock.
"Tell me about
the CDLC," and so forth.
And I can now ask questions and get clarification.
This is hopefully — fingers crossed —
like I'm talking with the speaker, using those quotes
and potentially other information from outside as well.
Okay.
So this is going to be available for every single session, live,
that we do at Dev Con — a little bit of fun. A couple of other things.
What I — when we do this within Tessl —
the first thing — in fact, let me go back to the app.
The first thing I do: we create the skill and we publish it
to the registry.
If I go to the history, I added this just today.
I build the skill
and I publish it to the registry as version 1.0.1.
Then I review the skill, because
one of the big questions is: how do we know if this skill is any good?
So I review it.
And that basically checks if the skill meets the best practices —
the quality that, you know, we have seen from
Anthropic best practices — I think not Codex — best practices
that they have published — and it validates: is this similar to those
best practices? It makes those changes.
Then it performs optimisation.
And optimisation is really about the impact that this skill makes.
In other words: if I was to ask this question
without the skill, would the agent alone be able to provide me
with a good enough answer?
So we run the same tests with and without,
and we identify how much of an impact that is.
So we do all of that, and then we can provide that.
If I go back to the Tessl registry, you can see right now
this is 1.3x times better than without the skill.
You can see the quality has gone up to 90% from
my original version — from my original 82%.
So we're identifying what are the best practices we're missing,
and then how can we update with those best practices?
Okay, I'll mention —
actually, we also run a security scan on this skill.
This is Tessl, but this is not Tessl.
I used to run at Snyk.
I used to — I used to work at Snyk for like six years.
I keep referring to Tessl as Snyk.
I'm just starting, after two years at Tessl,
to refer to Snyk as Tessl now, so I think it's balancing out.
But this is a security report — a security scan run by Snyk —
trying to identify it using LLM as a judge here, trying to identify
potential malicious issues or bad security practices within my skill.
And it will provide me — if I go here to my security — it will provide me
with any security issues that could exist there in my evals.
Oh, why is that?
I need to go to my correct version.
In my evals, you can see where things are good
and where things are bad, and in some cases where things
actually regress — where my context confuses the agent.
And so this gives us insight into what the context
is doing a good job at, and where we need to actually improve.
Okay, let's jump back to
slides — and I'll — where's my slides? — here.
And I'll flip through a couple of additional.
Why you're not working —
there we go.
And I'll flip through a couple of important things
that we should be considering as we start scaling our usage of skills —
or really even as an organisation or as an individual.
So here are some scenarios.
I've got six scenarios that we need to think about.
Whether we use Tessl or something else,
we should have a mechanism in place where we know how we can achieve these things.
Your team or company, right?
Hundreds of skills.
They're not — but they're local.
Essentially, each developer is writing them locally and using them locally.
They're not discoverable by others.
How do we unlock the value that one individual gets, and effectively
multiply that across a team or across an organisation?
So a really important way — we need some registry.
We need some mechanism where others can find those types of skills.
Your team installs loads of skills.
Every developer has a different set of skills developing on the same project.
How do you achieve consistency across the whole project?
So maybe your organisation says, "You know what?
We need these skills always to be on" — always-on
skills across every single team in our organisation.
That's important to mandate.
Also, if I have a set of skills that I want everyone to use as a project —
maybe it uses third-party library dependencies, maybe it needs to use
a proprietary context for a proprietary library that I've developed.
That context should be available to everyone.
Otherwise, imagine lots of developers
on a team, all using different levels of knowledge.
Some people don't even know about proprietary libraries.
Some people do. You just wouldn't have it.
You'd constantly have pull request reviews saying, "You have to use this."
We don't want to do it to people. We don't want to do it to agents, either.
I've got loads of skills installed.
Are they being used correctly?
Activation is a key, key problem, and I'll talk about that
in just a second, actually.
But how do I tell if my agent is actually activating?
That's such a key, key piece.
Because there's no point
getting our skills to be really good if we actually don't use them in practice.
Dev teams install skills from everywhere.
How do we audit
and ensure we're not using poor security skills or malicious skills?
This is all about the scanning — whether via Snyk directly or through a registry.
So, so important from an audit point of view. We haven't yet hit that
"Oh shit, someone's deployed a malicious skill
and it's really having problems in a production environment."
It's a headline waiting to happen.
This is a key one.
You're after a specific skill.
You know, there are five developers who've all created the same skill.
There's probably 20 more who have created other skills.
Which one do you use?
Which one is malicious?
Which one is the highest quality?
Which one has the biggest impact?
You need to be able to understand which are the better skills,
and you need to be able to track where there are multiple skills
and how you actually remove those skills from view.
And finally, where you do
get a bunch of skills — typically what you'll do is you'll get stale states,
whereby things are moving on, certain things are stale.
How do you keep that up to date?
And this is very much thinking about context as code.
You want to maintain that — as your code changes, your context changes.
As models change, your context will need to change,
because models will learn more, they'll know better, and your context
will maybe need to remove things because the agents are good.
So those are some things about how we scale.
The last thing I want to talk about — and I'll do this in just a few minutes — is
how, when we are building skills, there are things that we should think about when
we actually create the skills ourselves and actually write the skills.
And we've learned this because — you know, in fact —
when we first gave this presentation, AI Engineer in London —
this was the rate of skill growth in 14 weeks.
We went from 12 skills in GitHub in November
up to, you know, 5,500 skills in just 14 weeks.
And it's probably way beyond that.
We could probably refresh that number now.
The key stat is: once a skill gets
added into GitHub, nine times out of ten it never gets updated.
What are the chances of that skill being perfect out of the box?
Virtually zero, right?
So what do we do about it?
Well, we decided to go on a mass pull request submission,
which I guess some people loved.
Some people didn't love quite as much, but we were trying to help.
And so we raised 622 pull requests.
And we essentially kind of said, "Look,
there's a whole bunch of things that we know are wrong with your skill.
Can we send a pull request to try and make suggestions to help?"
And from that we learnt what are the key things
that most people are failing at in their skill creation.
The first one — and this is probably the biggest problem
that developers generally have — is thinking,
"If I just write a crappy description because it's a description,
I'll get away with it and I don't actually need it."
But this is actually really, really important.
And there are a number of things that are important within the description as well.
If you can make that description specific to maybe tools that you use
or technology that you use, the agent has a higher chance of using it,
because it has less in its memory and in its training data
about this specific tool or this specific use case.
So it's more likely to inject the skill context into that.
So before, we very often see, you know, "A helpful skill for code review and quality
improvement" — an agent knows how to do that already, or it thinks it does.
But after, you're talking about running ESLint with project rules —
you know, this is very specific, and it gets triggered much, much more.
Here's quite a shocking stat.
Only 40% — 41% of times — will a skill activate
if an agent isn't forced to use a skill. And by "forced
to use a skill," we're talking about using a slash command in a task.
So if you just say, "I want to do this thing" and a skill exists,
will that agent actually activate that skill to do it, or will it
try and do it itself? 41% won't.
And there are many reasons.
One of which is "god skills" — a skill
that tries to do everything: the one all-encompassing skill.
And there are a few reasons
why this can fail — particularly with an activation one — because,
well, actually, if there are 50 things and I have a specific
task, it might well activate a completely different skill in my plugin.
There's just too much overlap between a number of skills.
It'll either do that, or it just won't activate at all.
Context bloat is another one,
and this is where you actually put so much context into your skill
that the agent won't actually pull the right pieces from it, typically.
And this is actually a best practice with Anthropic and so forth.
They talk about keeping your SKILL.md below
500 lines. Optimised skills,
interestingly, use 40% fewer tokens
and complete tasks in half the time.
And this is about either removing duplication or removing
things that the agent most likely knows how to do anyway.
And so all of this is about running evals
and making sure your skill is all it can be.
And that's everything.
I hope that wasn't too long, but there's a ton more in this type of
session.
And perhaps I can share with you a full deck afterwards as well.
I've got time for questions.
Yeah, a little bit, a little bit.
A very short question.
Anyone have any questions or comments? Yes.
Do we have a queue over there?
My question is, you said 41%. Have you
tried anything like force skill usage?
I remember — for Anthropic ones you can use hooks to say, like, every turn,
basically go check if you need to use a skill, or anything like that.
Or is there anything else?
Yeah.
So I mean, you can — the best way to force it —
well, even if you use a hook and there are 100 skills that you have
installed, the hook then still has to determine what the best skill to use is.
And it might be that it's just not used the right skill, because it's
way too complicated to work out which the right skill is.
So I think you could use hooks,
you could enforce use of a skill by using a slash command.
But I think the biggest value,
the biggest bang for your buck, is fixing the description
and actually fixing the way you bundle skills together.
So breaking them up to make sure you haven't got so many skills
that it's just confusing — or, you know, bringing smaller skills together
so that when you have a number of things
that you always want to do together, maybe that actually fits
in a single skill.
But I would say — you know —
you can't improve on something you can't measure.
So I think the biggest key is: run evaluations.
So we — as part of our new skill optimiser —
we run activation tests as well.
And we have insights that show when your skills are getting activated as well.
So I would say: make sure
you have a plan for measurement, and then try to improve that.
That could be hooks, but I think there are
low-hanging fruit first, and then hooks afterwards to say, "Hey,
could you have improved this with a skill, and which skill would it be?"
Maybe you have a list of skills to use, but you're almost duplicating work there.
Yeah. Thank you. Cool.
Perhaps just one more. Yeah.
Gentleman, just —
Higher.
Wait for the presentation.
What about — have you thought about, let's say, conflict?
So let's say if you have an element model —
okay —
as you know that
if — let's say we talk about humans — let's say you have two concepts,
but they're conflicting between those two models.
Yeah.
I mean, two thoughts — let's say in the beginning, then we would actually
lay them out on a piece of paper and then basically do a comparison of sorts, right?
Right.
So if I do that, that happened — that that happened.
But with an LLM, I think — do you think that
that can be a huge conflict over —
either conflict of interest or conflict between two skills at the
same time? I absolutely think so.
And I think it gets to the stage where it's almost inevitable,
once you start adding lots and lots of skills to your environment.
It's one thing that we are looking to add into our platform
for the more enterprise-style deployments,
because they will have — we think they will have — so many skills.
What this needs to be is — it's
a hard thing to test, first of all, because you can't test them in isolation.
It'll typically be when you install 50 skills
from so many different places that all of a sudden you have two people
with differing opinions, and it has to pick one over the other.
Or weirdly, it merges the two,
and actually you're not satisfying either skill.
So what you then need is two things: first of all,
conflict detection — to be able to say, "Okay, you've got two skills here that
have a difference of opinion."
Or even in similarity sometimes.
Yeah, it could be. Yeah.
But then you need a merge resolution.
And so it's like, "Okay, which one should win?"
And it's like — maybe the agent should — you can describe something with the agent.
But more likely what it is:
you need a path to remove that conflict.
So you need to either start removing a skill or adapting a skill
so that it removes the conflict.
But I think we're at the earliest stage
where people are just starting to throw skills in.
It's something that's bound to happen, and we can only kick the can down the road
a little bit before it truly happens at a larger scale, for sure.
Yeah. Great questions.
Thank you. Thank you very much. No worries.
At least I got to pique your interest. Yeah.
These are definitely things
we've pondered.
Awesome. I think I'm done for questions —
sorry — but I'll be here.
I'll be here. I'm here all night.
I'm here all week.
So I'm going to yield to the next speaker.
But I appreciate everyone's attention on a beautifully sunny day.
So thank you very much.
Oh!